What would it take to manufacture a long
lasting and repairable smartphone, but
one that sources material and labor as
ethically as possible? The folks at
Fairphone founded their company in 2013
based on that question, and the
Fairphone 6 is the most refined answer
they've provided yet. As we've come to
expect from Fairphone, we already have a
nice selection of parts and repair
manuals available for the Fairphone 6
and a commitment to provide 7 years of
Android software upgrades and 8 years of
security updates. And in addition to the
5-year warranty, Fairphone runs a
loyalty program that rewards consumers
for each repair performed, and every
year they continue to own their
smartphone. There are trade-offs in the
hardware. They've implemented USB 2
instead of USB 3 to reduce production
costs, and the camera sensors perform
well, but won't quite measure up to
flagship tier products. But if you're
looking for a device that puts people on
planet before profits, then this may
well be it. Now, Fairphone's phones are
predominantly aimed at the European
market, but US customers can get their
hands on one of these things through the
partnership with Marina. So, let's dive
in and see how Fairphone made a
repairable device. Starting with
everybody's favorite consumable
component, the battery. The back cover
is held in place by two T5 torque
screws, the only screw type used
throughout. Once those are out, the
cover slides away. Inside, there are
four screws securing the battery and one
up top securing a plastic cover. With
the flex cable disconnected, the battery
is free to come out. Using screws to
secure the battery beats glue every
single time, easy to remove and easy to
replace. With a typical capacity of
17.26 W hours, the battery is glued to a
thin strip of metal designed to be light
in weight and resource consumption,
while sturdy enough to protect a lithium
ion pouch from unintended impact. Once
the battery is out, it's time to take a
look at another commonly replaced
component of the screen. The top half of
the back cover is only held in place by
clips. now that the battery is out. So,
I'll remove that first. The eight silver
screws securing the screen are now fully
revealed and can be removed.
That frees the screen from the housing
and reveals the single screw and bracket
underneath the screen itself that
secured the ribbon cable to the main
board. There's no glue here, and that's
one of the reasons why this phone is
IP55 rated. But on the upside, this is
one of the easiest screen removal
processes I've ever seen. The beautiful
6.31 in LTPO OLED display is slightly
smaller than the Fairphone 5 6.46 in
display, but it has nearly double the
peak brightness and a variable refresh
rate from 10 to 120 hertz, enabling low
power always on functionality. So,
there's no question that this is the
superior screen. Next up, the USBC port.
Removing the speaker assembly
immediately gives me access to the
highly modular USBC port, which is
awesome if you ever have a failure due
to mechanical wear. I've removed every
major failure point from this section of
the phone, but for the sake of
completing the tear down, it's worth
noting that the daughterboard is also
modular and easily replaceable. The
warning label here sits on top of the
coax cables running down from the
mainboard. And while mainboard and
daughterboard replacements aren't going
to be a typical repair for most, it's
nice to know it's easily possible. But
the front-facing camera and the twin
rearfacing cameras are all immediately
accessible the moment I pop their
protective plastic cover off.
I'm disconnecting everything in sight
from the earpiece speaker, ultrawide
camera, the 50 megapixel main camera,
and all the way down to the interconnect
and coax cables. For those that have
experienced it, camera repairs can be
difficult and expensive. So, being able
to perform this repair at home and on a
budget will have a meaningful impact on
the devices longevity. And it's not just
longevity. The modular and accessible
design means that component upgrades are
entirely possible, just like we saw on
the Fairphone 3. At this point, you
might be wondering what happened to that
third camera bump on the back case.
Well, that's not for a camera, but the
time offlight sensor that needs its own
window to the outside world to function
correctly. With all those components
out, there's nothing stopping me from
removing the mainboard. So, I'm going to
remove it. One reason why the mainboard
came away so easily is the use of pogo
pins, which removes the need for more
connectors and tiny screws. The downside
is that the contact pads are glued to
the frame. Add to that delicate ribbon
cables and you have a potentially fiddly
repair if you ever break the power
button.
And there you have it, a fully torn down
Fairphone 6, which I'm pleased to report
went back together and will continue to
function for many more years to come.
From ease of access to the battery to an
extremely repair-friendly screen, USBC
port, and camera assembly, this phone is
made with one stubborn mission in mind
to outlast anything else in the same
product category and set an example as
to what a fair product might look like.
From raw resources to end product and
well beyond. The Fronhoffer Institute
found that keeping a fair phone for 5
years instead of three cut the phone's
carbon footprint by around 1/3. And the
key to achieving that longevity is
making available the parts, manuals, and
software updates that consumers can
reasonably be expected to need nearly a
decade down the line. With these
extremely wellthoughtout and executed
design decisions in mind, the Fairphone
6 easily earns a 10 out of 10 for
repairability on iix smartphone
repairability scale, and we're very
happy to recommend it once more.